[
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 1,
        "year": 2000,
        "question": "<p>Highlight any three merits and any three demerits of democracy. <br>\n </p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong><em>(a) Merits of Democracy:</em></strong></p><p>(i)There is orderly transfer of power. People may resort to violence rather than to the ballot box, if there is no arrangement for orderly transfer of power.</p><p>(ii) Decisions reflect the wishes of the majority. The people have the opportunity to take part in the decisions of the government.</p><p>(iii) It provides for the rule of law, where everybody is equal before the law of the land.</p><p>(iv) It ensures political accountability of the rulers to the ruled, including the power of recall and replacement by the electorate.</p><p>(v) In a democracy, fundamental human rights are in place and guaranteed,.e.g. freedom of expression, association and assembly.</p><p>(iv) It equally guarantees the supremacy of the constitution. The actions of those in government are guided by the constitution.</p><p><em><strong>(b) Demerits of Democracy: </strong></em></p><p>(i) The existence of many political parties may lead to instability in government.</p><p>(ii) The opinion of the majority is usually forced on the people while the opinion of the minority is sometimes ignored.</p><p>(iii) Illiteracy and poverty make democracy difficult to practice because people may not be enlightened enough to fight for their rights or may be easily influenced by money and other material things.</p><p>(iv) Democracy is expensive to operate in terms of orgaisation of elections and maintenance of the legislature and other political institutions.</p><p>(v) It may lead to delay in taking decision, for example, the passing of 2000 budget in Nigeria. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 2,
        "year": 2000,
        "question": "<p>What are the functions of the Head of Government in a presidential system?<br>\n </p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong><em>Functions of the Head of Government in a presidential system: </em></strong></p><p>(i) The Head of Government initiates bills and policies for the approval of the parliament.</p><p>(ii) He supervises the implementation of Government policies by the civil servant and other government agencies.</p><p>(iii) He assents to bills passed by the legislature to become law.</p><p>(iv) The Head of Government prepares and presents annual budgets for parliamentary approval.</p><p>(v) He also appoints key officials of government, e.g. ministers, ambassadors, political or economic advisers, judges of the superior courts.</p><p>(vi) He represents and speaks for his country in international fora, e.g., U.N.O., O.A.U., ECOWAS, etc.</p><p>(vii) The Head of Government confers national awards on deserving citizens.</p><p>(viii) He signs treaties with foreign states and receives foreign dignitaries.</p><p>(ix) He acts as the Head of State and Commander-in-Chief of the armed forces.</p><p>(x) He exercises the power of prerogative of mercy e.g. pardon for someone who has offended the state.</p><p>(xi) He has the right to declare a state of emergency in the country when the situation demands.<br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 3,
        "year": 2000,
        "question": "<p>Why is election necessary in a democratic state?<br>\n </p>",
        "answer": "<p><em><strong>Reasons why election is necessary in a democratic State. </strong></em></p><p>(i) Avenue for choosing representatives: Election presents a sound avenue for choosing representatives.</p><p>(ii) Accountability: It makes rulers accountable to the electorate.</p><p>(iii) Existence of the opposition: It allows the opposition group to act as watchdog over the activities of the government.</p><p>(iv) It provides a conducive atmosphere for changing governments at periodic intervals.</p><p>(v) Political edu-cation: It makes it possible for the electorate to receive political education.</p><p>(vi) Election is a check to excesses of government. It discourages obnoxious policies inimical to good government. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 4,
        "year": 2000,
        "question": "<p> In what five ways is the civil service different from the public corporations?<br>\n </p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong><em>The following are ways in which the Civil Service is different from the public Corporations</em></strong></p><p>(i) Managed by a board of directors, the civil service is Managed by a minister who is advised by the permanent secretary.</p><p>(ii) Employees are called public servants while Employees are called civil servants in the civil service</p><p>(iii) Administrative head is designated General Manager / Managing Director. in the civil service, The Administrative head is the permanent secretary.</p><p>(iv) Expected to provide services, break even and, in some cases, make profit. civil servants Provides services with no profit motive.</p><p>(v) Does not pay its revenue into consolidated fund. civil service Pays its revenue into the consolidated fund</p><p>(vi) Workers are appointed or employed by the board of service commission. Workers are employed by civil / public directors in the civil service.</p><p>(vi) Provides social services and amenities. The civil service Assists the government in the formulation and implementation of policies.</p><p>(viii) Chairman acts as political head. Minister is the political head in the civil service.</p><p>(ix) Can sue and be sued. civil servants Can only sue and be sued through the Attorney- General.</p><p>(x) Is self-financing except the initial capital provided by the government. civil service Obtains finances from the annual budget.</p><p>(xi) Established by statutes or acts of the Legislature. The civil service Does not owe its existence to statutes. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 5,
        "year": 2000,
        "question": "<p>Describe any five problems associated with a single party system of government.<br>\n </p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong><em>Problems Associated with single party System of Government. </em></strong></p><p>(i) Dictatorship: A one-party system leads to dictatorship and oppression.</p><p>(ii) Political education: There is a limit to political education in the system.</p><p>(iii) Public opinion: The system neglects the opinion of the public that is opposed to party policy.</p><p>(iv) The rule of law: The system ignores the principle of the rule of law.</p><p>(v) It is undemocratic: This is because it does not allow for freedom of choice.</p><p>(vi) No opposition: The system discourages open criticism of government policies. In fact, there is no opposition.</p><p>(vii) Instability: A one-party system leads to political instability.</p><p>(viii) Change of government: Change of government is not always smooth and peaceful.</p><p>(ix) Autocratic government: A single party system creates an elitist or autocratic government. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 6,
        "year": 2000,
        "question": "<p>In what five ways have political parties contributed to the constitutional development of Nigeria?<br>\n </p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong><em>The ways political parties contributed to the constitutional Development of Nigeria. </em></strong></p><p>(i) Political parties provided the leadership for constitutional development. Their members spearheaded agitation for constitutional reforms. For example, the 1946 Richard Constitution in Nigeria was criticized for lack of consultation.</p><p>(ii) The political parties initiated popular opposition against colonial government, for example, the Richards Constitution of 1951</p><p>(iii) They provided political education through rallies and newspapers owned by their leaders and these enlightened the masses on the deficiencies of colonial constitutions, e.g.. West African Pilot, Comet, Lagos Weekly Record, Nigeria Tribune, e.t.c.</p><p>(iv) Provision of leaders: The political parties provided leaders who attended constitutional conferences for the attainment of political independence, e.g. the ibadan,Conference of 1951 and the London Conferences of 1953 and 1957.</p><p>(v) Formation of government: They formed governments in their various regions under the 1951 constitution. This formed the basis for self-government in 1957 and 1959 and the eventual independence in 1960.<br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 7,
        "year": 2000,
        "question": "<p>Why was indirect Rule not successful in some parts of Nigeria? <br>\n </p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong><em>Reasons why Indirect Rule was not successful in some parts of Nigeria.</em></strong></p><p>(i) Absence of centralized form of administration: There was no such system among the Ibo of Eastern Nigeria and therefore, there was nothing for the system to hold on to.</p><p>(ii) There was no tax system in some parts. For example, in Yoruba land and among the Ibo people, the attempt at introducing taxation resulted in riots</p><p>(iii) Opposition: There was opposition from educated elites, mostly because they were not allowed to take part in the administration.</p><p>(iv) Imposition of rulers: Equally, there was opposition to the imposition of non-traditional rulers or warrant chiefs among the Ibo people.</p><p>(v) Nationalist activities: There was rapid growth of nationalist activities in the South, which resulted in protests and demonstration against the system.</p><p>(vi) Chieftaincy institutions: Chieftaincy was degraded by giving menial jobs to chiefs, e.g. tax collection in I Yoruba and Igbo land.<br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 8,
        "year": 2000,
        "question": "<p>What were the functions of the colonial Governor in British West Africa? <br>\n </p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong><em>Functions of the Colonial Governor in British West Africa. </em></strong></p><p>(i)Appointment: He appointed, promoted and disciplined or dismissed public servants in the colony.</p><p>(ii) Formulation of policies: He formulated social and economic policies for the colony.</p><p>(iii) Meetings: The colonial governor presided over the meetings of both the legislative and the executive councils.</p><p>(iv) Assent: He assented to all bills passed by the legislative council.</p><p>(v) Allocation of land: He approved the allocation of land acquired by the government.</p><p>(vi) Power of government: He exercised all the powers of Head of Government on behalf of the British, e.g. declaration of state of emergency, the exercise of the prerogative of mercy.</p><p>(vii) Reserved powers: He exercised reserved powers in making laws for the colonies, e.g. powers of veto and certification.</p><p>(viii) Appointment of members of the executive and legislative councils: He appointed some of the members of these two arms of government including the ex-officio members.</p><p>(ix) Report to the Crown: He reported to the crown through the secretary of state for the colonies.</p><p>(x) Ceremonial functions: The governor performed ceremonial functions, e.g., conferment of honors and receiving of dignitaries. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 9,
        "year": 2000,
        "question": "<p>Trace the evolution of federalism in Nigeria from 1914 to 1954. <br>\n </p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong><em>The Evolution of Federalism in Nigeria from 1914 -1954. </em></strong></p><p>(i) In 1914, Lord Lugard amalgamated the colony and protectorate of Southern Nigeria and the protectorate of Northern Nigeria, mainly for economic reasons.</p><p>(ii) In 1922 a constitution named Clifford Constitution was promulgated. The constitution provided for legislative council for the colony and Southern protectorate of Nigeria. The Northern region was excluded from the council. The elective principle introduced paved way for political parties only in the South.</p><p>(iii) ln 1946, another Constitution named after Arthur Richards was promulgated. The Constitution introduced regionalism under which the country was divided into three regions -North, West and East. There was, however, no constitutional division of powers. Regional assemblies had no legislative powers.</p><p>(iv) In 1951 the Macpherson Constitution introduced a quasi-federal system which gave legislative powers on specific issues to the regional government but subject to the ratification of the central government.</p><p>(v) The 1954 Lyttleton Constitution formally established an improved quasi-federal system which divided legislative powers into exclusive, concurrent and residual lists. Premiers were appointed to head the three regions. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 10,
        "year": 2000,
        "question": "<p>Distinguish between the 1963 Constitution and 1979 Constitution of Nigeria. <br>\n </p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong><em>Factors which distinguish between the 1963 Constitution and 1979 Constitution of Nigeria.</em></strong></p><p>(i) The 1963 Republican Constitution provided for parliamentary or cabinet system of government while the 1979 constitution made provision for presidential / executive system.</p><p>(ii) In 1963, the real executive powers were vested in the council of ministers headed by the prime minister while all executive powers were vested in the president under the 1979 Constitution.</p><p>(iii) In the 1963 Constitution, there was difference between Head of State and Head of government as well as Commander-in-Chief of the Armed Forces.</p><p>(iv) In the 1963 Constitution, some members of the legislature were also members of the executive, but in 1979, members of the executive were not members of the legislature.</p><p>(v) Collective responsibility of the cabinet to the legislature was a common feature of the 1963 Constitution while in the 1979 Constitution, ministers were personally responsible to the president.</p><p>(vi) In the 1963 Constitution, there was no uniform local government system while the 1979 Constitution provided for a uniform local government system.</p><p>(vii) The 1963 Constitution provided for bicameral legislature in the states while 1979 constitution made provision for unicameralism in the states.</p><p>(viii) The 1963 Constitution had no fixed number of terms for the office of the president and prime minister (a term was five years) but in the 1979 Constitution, the president was limited to two terms of four years each.<br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 11,
        "year": 2000,
        "question": "<p>What are the guiding principle s of the Organization of African Unity (OAU)? <br>\n </p>",
        "answer": "<p><em><strong>Principles of the Organisation of African Unity (OAU). </strong></em></p><p>(i) No interference whatsoever, in the internal affairs of members states.</p><p>(ii) Unreserved condemnation of subversive activities among members states.</p><p>(iii) Disputes among member states should be settled through negotiation, mediation, conciliation or arbitration.</p><p>(iv)Absolute dedication to the emancipation of African territories still under colonial rule.</p><p>(v) Every member state has the right of independent existence irrespective of size. Its territory must be free from external attack or annexation by any other member.</p><p>(vi) The policy of non-alignment to all blocs should be strictly pursued.</p><p>(vii) All member states are equal; no state would be too big to dominate others and no state would be too small to be recognized. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "government",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 12,
        "year": 2000,
        "question": "<p>Describe any four benefits member states of the Commonwealth derive from the Organization. <br>\n </p>",
        "answer": "<p><strong><em>Benefits Member States of the Commonwealth derive from the Organisation:</em></strong></p><p>(i) Member states enjoy technical, scientific and educational benefits: For example, countries like Britain, Canada, Australia, etc, offer scholar-ship schemes to other countries yearly.</p><p>(ii) Grants and Aids: Commonwealth member states give grants and aids to other countries. For instances Canada helped to finance Nigeria's telecommunication system.</p><p>(iii) Trade: Member countries enjoy trade cooperation as they sign trade agreements.</p><p>(iv) English Language: The common use of English Language among member states serves as a unifying factor.</p><p>(v) Important forum: The commonwealth acts as an important forum where member states meet to discuss matters of common concern.</p><p>(vi) Military assistance: Member state enjoys military assistance from one another in the form of equipment, military hardware, technical advice and training.</p><p>(vii) Friendship and cooperation: Member-states enjoy friendship and cooperation through Commonwealth games and other social activities.</p><p>(viii) Legal system: Member states practice similar legal system, e.g., the use of the British common law and court structures. <br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    }
]